A Guide to the Papers of Bertha Fanning Taylor 1915-1979
Special Collections and University Archives, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Old Dominion University
Papers of Bertha Fanning Taylor 1915-1979
Special Collections and University Archives, Old Dominion University
MG 44
3 Hollinger Documents Cases
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Norman Taylor, Jr. on July 3, 1981
Biographical/Historical Information
Bertha Fanning Taylor was born on July 30, 1883 in New York City. She was the daughter of Spencer A. Fanning and Mary A. Switt. In 1889, she moved to Spotswood, New Jersey after her mother's death. In 1896, she attended Hunter College in New York. Upon graduation, Mrs. Taylor studied under Bryson Burroughs at the Women's Art School of Cooper Union in New York City where she received a certificate in 1903.
In 1908, Bertha Fanning married Norman Taylor who was Assistant Curator at the New York Botanical Gardens. The next year, Bertha Fanning Taylor and her husband went on a trip to the West Indies for botanical studies. In 1924, she went to Montpellier, France with her two daughters. From 1929-1933, Mrs. Taylor studied at L'Ecole du English-speaking groups at the Louvre and became assistant to the Art Editor in Paris for The American Herald. In this period, Mrs. Taylor exhibited many of her own works in major salons in Paris.
In 1933, Mrs. Taylor visited her daughter frequently in Rome and visited major art centers of Italy. At the outbreak of World War II, she lived for two months in Rome, but returned to the United States and lived in Greenwich Village.
Upon leaving New York in 1945, Mrs. Taylor came to Norfolk as Curator of the Sloane collection at the Heritage Foundation Museum. In 1948, she taught extension courses in art appreciation, art history, painting and drawing for the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary (presently Old Dominion University) until 1951. During this period Mrs. Taylor in 1950 began teaching classes in painting and drawing at the, Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences, as well as classes at the YWCA until 1960. She then opened her own studio.
In 1963, Mrs. Taylor was awarded the medal of the Order of the Palmes Academique by the French government for efforts in the founding of Salon Francais of the Women's Club in Norfolk, In 1966, Mrs. Taylor had a one person show at the Norfolk Museum of Arts of Sciences of graphic work, including drawings, etchings and wood block prints.
Mrs. Taylor published two works. The first was in 1963 entitled Form and Feeling in-Painting and the second in 1968 entitled My Fifteen Years in France. From 1968 to 1977 Mrs. Taylor was very active in the Norfolk Women's Club and taught students on a personal basis.
In 1977 Mrs. Taylor sustained a fall and stayed in the hospital for many weeks and then lived at the Medi-Center nursing home until her death on July 3, 1980.
A long time friend of Mrs. Taylor, Mr. Benjamin F. Clymer of the Reference Department at Old Dominion University summarized Mrs. Taylor as, "Blue Blood, Blue Stocking, and True Blue with the brilliance of gold and the warmth of red."
Scope and Content Information
The Bertha Fanning Taylor Papers span the years from 1915 to 1979 and is a collection of literary productions, printed materials, correspondence, scrapbooks, charts, photographic materials, and memorabilia. A wealth of information in art and art forms is available in the collection. In addition to the artistic significance of the papers, the collection has a significance in the history of Norfolk, especially in the Arts.
Organization
Series I is made up of the literary productions produced by Bertha Fanning Taylor, including notes, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, periodical clippings and reminiscences. Because of the nature of the collection, the series is arranged by subject. Of special significance is a manuscript produced by Mrs. Taylor entitled, "Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972." (see Box 1 folders 9 through 15).
Series II consists of printed materials. This series contains: certificates, newspaper clippings, periodical clippings, programs, publications, circulars and brochures. Alphabetical arrangement according to subject was maintained.
Series III is correspondence. Because of the scarcity of letters, arrangement is chronological.
Series IV is a scrapbook. It contains many news clippings. Of special interest is a letter to Mrs. Taylor from Mrs. Lyndon B. Johnson.
Series V are charts that contain hand-drawn furniture styles.
Series VI contains photographic material. Most of the photographs are of Mrs. Taylor's works in painting and drawing. A chronological arrangement is maintained.
Series VII consists of memorabilia. It contains invitations, tickets, book marks, postcards and sketches. The series contains two sketches, most likely to be original works by Mrs. Taylor; however neither sketch is signed.
Contents List
- Literary Productions
  - Notes
    - Artists (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Art Styles (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Book Notes (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Greek Notes (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - History-Chronologies (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Murals (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Religion and Art (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sciences (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts
    - Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972: 12 Chapters-Chapters 1 and 2 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972: 12 Chapters-Chapters 3, 4, and 5 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972: 12 Chapters-Chapters 6 and 7 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972: 12 Chapters-Chapters 8, 9, and 10 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Building Anew at Sixty Years in a Southern City; A Book of Memories by Bertha Fanning Taylor from 1939 to 1972: 12 Chapters-Chapters 11 and 12 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - French Primitive Painting (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Letter to Editor/"Etchings by John Taylor Arms" (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Periodical Clippings
    - "Around the Art Galleries", series of articles by Bertha Fanning Taylor (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reminiscences
    - "Thoughts on Painting"/Short Autobiography (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
- Printed Materials
  - Certificates
    - Women's School of Art, New York June 3, 1905 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Clippings-Italian July 1939-March 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Clippings-French (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Artists (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Glass (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Japanese Crown Prince Akihito/Elizabeth Gray Vining (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Rembrandt (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Van Dyck (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Reviews (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Sculpture (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mrs. Taylor (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Obituaries (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Periodical Clippings
    - Miscellaneous 1942-1966 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs
    - Lectures offered by Bertha Fanning Taylor (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Exhibit Programs for Bertha Fanning Taylor 1966-1977 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum Schedules for France 1934-1936 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - U.S. Museums (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - General (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Publications
    - Color by Clara Dudley (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Himself and I by Mary Sinton Leitch (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - La Divina Commedia (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Life of Forms in Art by Henri Focillion (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Life of Michelangelo by Morgan (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Rime by Michaelangelo Buonarotti (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Song in Their Hearts by Grace Shepherd Ferebee (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Twenty-Five Poems by Adam Mickiewicz (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Circulars-Pantheon Art Publication Prices (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Brochures-"A Guide to Authors" C and P Telephone (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence
  - General Miscellaneous 1938-1950 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - Green bound scrapbook-clippings and of a special note: a letter to Mrs. Taylor from Mrs. Lyndon B. Johnson (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
- Charts
  - Furniture Styles (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
- Photographic Material
  - Positive Prints
    - Paintings by Bertha Fanning Taylor ca. 1930s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Paintings by Bertha Fanning Taylor 1946-1966 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Mrs. Taylor and Friends ca. 1960s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mrs. Taylor and Friends undated (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Negative Transparencies
    - Mexican cities by Early Settlers undated (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Invitations to Art Premires and Previews (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tickets from Italy (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hand Painted Book Marks (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Post cards of Paintings (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Two untitled sketches (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)